<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en-us">
  <title type="text">Press Releases » Camp for Climate Action</title>

  <link rel="self" href="http://climatecamp.org.uk/press_releases.atom" />
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://climatecamp.org.uk/press_releases" />

  <id>http://climatecamp.org.uk/press_releases</id>
  <updated>2011-04-14T10:38:00Z</updated>
  <author><name>Camp for Climate Action</name></author>
  
  
    <entry>
      <published>2011-04-14T10:38:00Z</published>
      <updated>2011-04-14T10:38:00Z</updated>
      <title>Judges slams kettling of G20 climate protesters as ‘unlawful’</title>
      <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://climatecamp.org.uk/press/2011/04/14/judges-slams-kettling-of-g20-climate-protesters-as-%E2%80%98unlawful%E2%80%99" />
      <id>http://climatecamp.org.uk/press/2011/04/14/judges-slams-kettling-of-g20-climate-protesters-as-%E2%80%98unlawful%E2%80%99</id>
      <content type="html">
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://photo.climatecamp.org.uk/gallery1/source/image/russell_010409_060.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;G20 Climate Camp&quot; width=&quot;568&quot; height=&quot;391&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a high-court ruling today Sir Anthony May, President of the Queens Bench Division, and Mr Justice Sweeney stated that containment of climate protesters on April 1st 2009 was &amp;ldquo;not lawful&amp;rdquo; (1).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the G20 protest over 4,000 climate campers occupied a stretch of Bishopsgate outside the European Climate Exchange. At 7 pm the police &amp;lsquo;kettled&amp;rsquo; the camp, and in the early hours of the morning violently evicted the protesters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Footage of the police violent eviction went viral on the internet with footage on YouTube being viewed 500,000 times (2).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Frances Wright of the Camp for Climate Action Legal Team said, &amp;ldquo;This is a brilliant result and I hope will act as some restraint on the macho policing of protest.&amp;nbsp; When, what the police call containment, is combined with forcible compression of a crowd, it is dangerous and injuries are almost inevitable.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Josh Moos one of three protesters who brought the Judicial Review against the police said, &amp;ldquo;Their behaviour was completely disproportionate. Yet again the police have been shown to be acting illegally in relation to climate change protesters.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the verdict the judges said of kettling, &amp;ldquo;&amp;ldquo;The police may only take such preventive action as a last resort catering for situations about to descend into violence.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Court the police said the containment was done in order to prevent people from the protest at the Bank of England joining them and causing a breach of the peace.&amp;nbsp; The protestors stated that the police&amp;rsquo;s approach was unnecessary and unlawful and that inadequate thought had been given to alterative options.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Climate Camp previously won a Judicial Review against illegal police behaviour in 2008.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Frances Wright said, &amp;ldquo;Effective protest, like the climate movement, seems to acquire disproportionate policing, as we can see by the recent arrests of UK Uncut activists at Fortnum and Masons recently. I urge other protest groups, like the students, who have also face political policing, to monitor the police and challenge them through the courts. Perhaps then we will see the right to protest being properly upheld.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The climate campers challenged the kettling at 7pm, the use of force, and the subsequent dispersal of the protest under s14 of the Public Order Act 1996.&amp;nbsp; They were represented in the judicial review proceedings in the High Court by Mike Fordham QC from Blackstones chambers and John Halford from Bindmans solicitors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Court&amp;rsquo;s final conclusion was&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;In the result, the claimants succeed in establishing that (a) the containment of the Climate Camp, and (b) the pushing operation to move the crowd 30m. to the north at the southern end of the Climate Camp were not lawful police operations.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;The demonstrators were represented by John Halford of Bindmans solicitors. He said today:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Kettling and the police aggression that accompanies it has become a common feature of demonstrations, especially in London. It seems that the larger and more unconventional the protest, the readier the police are to trample on the protestors involved and their rights to express themselves. But this was a lawful assembly by people committed to highlighting the grave dangers of Climate Change. The Court has roundly condemned the unlawful and oppressive police response, exposing it as unacceptable in a democratic society. To date, there have been few signs of a change in police attitudes and tactics since G20. This judgement could not give a clearer signal that must happen immediately.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(1)&amp;nbsp; The verdict is available from the court, and will be available online later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(2) Reach your own view &amp;ndash; &amp;ldquo;riot police attack peaceful protesters at G20 Climate Camp&amp;rdquo; (598,843 views) &amp;ndash; 7.00pm, South end Bishopsgate &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=t244-zEENSs&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=t244-zEENSs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contacts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Participants are available for interview.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Frances Wright &amp;ndash; Climate Camp Legal Team:&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; 07973 186549.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Email: press@climatecamp.org.uk&lt;/p&gt;
      </content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <published>2011-04-13T11:03:00Z</published>
      <updated>2011-04-13T11:03:00Z</updated>
      <title>Response to Police Spy Documentary</title>
      <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://climatecamp.org.uk/press/2011/04/13/response-to-police-spy-documentary" />
      <id>http://climatecamp.org.uk/press/2011/04/13/response-to-police-spy-documentary</id>
      <content type="html">
        &lt;p&gt;Police spy Mark Kennedy infiltrated several movements but is best known for his infiltration of the climate movement. After selling his story to the Mail on Sunday it comes as no surprise that Kennedy has now cut a deal with a documentary film-maker. No surprise either that the Camp for Climate Action media team received an email from the documentary producer asking if we would like to be involved. Despite our usual willingness to talk to the media we have declined the offer. Let&amp;rsquo;s remember that Kennedy is a professional liar. He is so lost these days that in his most recent interview he claimed to be sad that there won&amp;rsquo;t be a climate camp this year - and that&amp;rsquo;s after systematically trying to disrupt Climate Camp activities for five years (which he clearly wasn&amp;rsquo;t very good at; Heathrow and Kingsnorth still don&amp;rsquo;t even have permission to be built).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is absolutely nothing to gain from appearing on TV next to an habitual liar. If Kennedy wants to make himself into a national TV talking-point on the psychological impacts of betrayal, that&amp;rsquo;s his choice. We&amp;rsquo;ll be sticking with action to tackle climate change.&amp;nbsp; That&amp;rsquo;s much more important than listening to Kennedy tie himself in contradictions to self-justify his seven years of deceit.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
      </content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <published>2011-03-21T12:00:00Z</published>
      <updated>2011-03-21T12:00:00Z</updated>
      <title>Metropolitan Police in Court over Protest Tactics</title>
      <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://climatecamp.org.uk/press/2011/03/21/metropolitan-police-in-court-over-protest-tactics" />
      <id>http://climatecamp.org.uk/press/2011/03/21/metropolitan-police-in-court-over-protest-tactics</id>
      <content type="html">
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Judicial review of G20 Climate Camp containment and dispersal operation held in Crown Court&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; Days before mass demonstrations against cuts, the Divisional Court scrutinises the legality of kettling and use of force at G20 . The three-day judicial review of the Metropolitan Police&amp;rsquo;s handling of the Camp for Climate Action at the G20 protests is to start on Tuesday. The claimants challenge decisions to kettle them, use of overwhelming violent force, and the dispersal of protesters before the Camp on Bishopsgate was due to come to an end. The test case is the first of&lt;br&gt; its kind to be considered by the Courts since the challenge to kettling at Oxford Circus on Mayday 2001.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; On April 1st 2009, the Camp for Climate Action occupied a stretch of Bishopsgate, outside the European Climate Exchange. At about 7.00pm the police cordoned off the area at both ends, and prevented people from entering and leaving. During the evening, the police made a number of forceful incursions into the camp using batons and what were&lt;br&gt; referred to in officers&amp;rsquo; notebooks as &amp;ldquo;tactics&amp;rdquo; such as &amp;ldquo;shield strikes&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;fist strikes&amp;rdquo;. Images of police violence provoked great controversy in the media. At about midnight hundreds of police dispersed everyone from the street, using dogs, riot gear and further violence. The police plan to open their case on Tuesday by arguing that a DVD showing the systemic use of unprovoked violence should be ruled inadmissible by the Court. It is understood they will argue what the DVD shows is not relevant to the case. &lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; The judicial review is challenging the decision of the police to initially contain the camp, the violent dispersal that took place in the early hours of the morning, and the police use of force against the camp. The judicial review is being taken by John Halford from Bindmans solicitors on behalf of two climate activists who were present at the camp, Josh Moos and Hannah McClure. He said today:&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; &amp;ldquo;Many countries around the world take their cue from Britain as to what is acceptable in terms of the policing of protests on the streets of their capitals. This case exposes the shameful fact that many police officers lack even a basic understanding of their proper role which is to facilitate - not suppress - non violent protest. That problem extends from the officers on the ground who used force on a peaceful crowd as a first resort, to their senior commanders, who gave no guidance that doing so was unacceptable. It is very troubling that the police continue to maintain that the policing of G20 was an overall success, and want to prevent the Court considering evidence that plainly shows that was not so.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; Trina Fellows, who was present at the Climate Camp during the police eviction in 2009 said:&lt;br&gt; &amp;ldquo;For all the controversy surrounding the G20 police tactics and the subsequent enquiries, very little seems to have changed. In the recent student protests, police officers were still not displaying their numbers, and indiscriminate kettling was still happening. We need this court case to hold the police accountable for the heavy handed, disproportionate political policing that is happening against protesters.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; Chief Superintendent Johnson, who was in command during the G20 protests is expected to be cross examined in court by the protesters&amp;rsquo; barrister, Mike Fordham, about the police decisions during the G20 protests.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; Following recent controversy over undercover policing of protest and the kettling of children on anti-fees demonstrations, the policing of protest is again going to be under public scrutiny at the end of this week as numerous groups are planning to occupy spaces and take direct action as part of the broader &amp;lsquo;March for the Alternative&amp;rsquo; demonstration planned by the TUC.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; Legal professionals have expressed concern that cases like this might not be possible in the future due to government proposals to dramatically cut legal aid.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; Frances Wright, from the Climate Camp legal team, said:&lt;br&gt; &amp;ldquo;The ability to challenge decisions of public authorities in this way is essential and it is often low income groups who need access the most; for protesters and all those affected by poor policing it is especially critical given the inadequacy of the police complaints system.&quot;&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.twitter.com/climatecamp&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
      </content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <published>2011-01-13T17:07:00Z</published>
      <updated>2011-01-13T17:07:00Z</updated>
      <title>Second police spy revealed - Climate Camp responds: We demand answers</title>
      <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://climatecamp.org.uk/press/2011/01/13/second-police-spy-revealed-climate-camp-responds-we-demand-answers" />
      <id>http://climatecamp.org.uk/press/2011/01/13/second-police-spy-revealed-climate-camp-responds-we-demand-answers</id>
      <content type="html">
        &lt;p&gt;A network of police agents undercover in the climate movement is today being dismantled after constabularies across Britain began an operation to pull out their spies. The revelation comes as the existence of a second spy is revealed &amp;ndash; demonstrating that the practice of placing undercover agents in activist circles was systematic, and proving that senior UK police officers lied to parliament about the tactic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leslie Marshall from the Camp for Climate Action today said:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;We welcome the collapse of the police spy network that for years has been targeting our movement and demand they stay out. These extraordinary revelations pose a number of profound questions that now need to be answered. So far the only inquiry that&amp;rsquo;s been announced will see the police investigating themselves, which is unacceptable given the indisputable evidence that officers have misled MPs and the public about the nature of their spying operation.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She continued:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;The first step must be that Paul Stephenson and Commander Bob Broadhurst stop stonewalling and give some answers for the conduct of operations they oversee. And they must be straight with us, not like parliament, when they stated&amp;nbsp; that there were no agents in the climate movement. In the longer term we need to ensure that the police are no longer taking political decisions to spend millions of pounds undermining a legitimate social movement taking action against the threat that climate change poses to us all.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keith Vaz, the chairman of the Commons home affairs select committee, has written to the Met commissioner, Sir Paul Stephenson, saying it appears the commissioner and one of his commanders, Bob Broadhurst, failed to disclose &amp;ldquo;the full facts&amp;rdquo; about the infiltration of protests when giving parliamentary evidence in 2009. &amp;ldquo;During our inquiry into the G20 protests, [MPs] explicitly asked Sir Paul Stephenson and commander Bob Broadhurst about the deployment of undercover officers,&amp;rdquo; said Vaz. &amp;ldquo;I am disappointed they appear not to have given us the full facts.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Policing of the climate movement has been severely criticized on numerous occasions since the first Climate Camp at Drax power station in 2006. In 2009 a report launched by the Liberal Democrat party found that police deliberately intimidated protesters and obstructed legal observers during protests at Kingsnorth coal plant. The activists were subjected to sleep deprivation and psychological pressure tactics involving frequent dawn raids, low flying helicopters at night, and repeated false alarm massing of police officers and vans, according to findings based on two separate reports submitted by the authors to the Joint Committee on Human Rights. The report highlighted that no Climate Camp protester has ever been convicted of any violent offence. However a separate IPCC investigation was, according to The Telegraph, &amp;lsquo;largely positive&amp;rsquo; about the Kingsnorth police operation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Charlie Horner added:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Serious issues, both moral and legal, are raised by Kennedy&amp;rsquo;s conduct over several years but we cannot allow the IPCC to conduct yet another whitewash. We need to know who in the Met knew what Kennedy was doing and when they knew it, why Kennedy was used to entrap so many activists at Ratcliffe, most of whom were never charged and six of whom he offered to support in court, and whether his wider conduct was sanctioned. The police can&amp;rsquo;t be held to a lower standard than everyone else in society. It&amp;rsquo;s time they were held to account.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
      </content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <published>2010-08-30T00:01:00Z</published>
      <updated>2010-08-30T00:01:00Z</updated>
      <title>Climate Activists Demand Answers from Lothian &amp; Borders Police</title>
      <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://climatecamp.org.uk/press/2010/08/30/climate-activists-demand-answers-from-lothian-borders-police" />
      <id>http://climatecamp.org.uk/press/2010/08/30/climate-activists-demand-answers-from-lothian-borders-police</id>
      <content type="html">
        &lt;p&gt;Activists from the Climate Camp, who set up camp at RBS headquarters at Gogarburn, Edinburgh last week, have filed a complaint today against the Lothian &amp;amp; Borders police force over unsubstantiated statements claiming that protestors from Climate Camp were responsible for an alleged oil spill on two main roads outside Edinburgh on Monday 23rd August 2010.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; The complaint demands an apology from Lothian &amp;amp; Borders Police for issuing two press releases accusing protesters of spilling oil on major roads, without providing any evidence linking the alleged 'oil spill' to climate activists. (1) Activists from the Camp claim that the police contravened both the Lothian &amp;amp; Borders Police Charter and the Scottish Police Service Code of Ethical Practice in failing to act 'fairly, honestly and with complete impartiality'. (2)&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; Activists from the Climate Camp are also filing Freedom of Information requests to Lothian &amp;amp; Borders Police for the Gold, Silver and Bronze command logs, police notebooks, and photographs of the scene.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; Climate Camp denies any knowledge of a connection between the Camp and the alleged 'oil spill', and have stated that it would be entirely uncharacteristic of Climate Camp actions, which neither endanger nor target the public.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; The letter to Lothian &amp;amp; Borders Police comes at the same time as a series of complaints to the Press Complaints Commission regarding 19 articles that published police allegations as fact.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; This is not the first time that the police have made false allegations as part of their press strategy regarding protests. The police's media strategy around the Kingsnorth Climate Camp in 2008 (3) and the G20 protests in London (April 2009) (4) were characterised by unsubstantiated accusations and media manipulation.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; The letter states:&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; &quot;This press strategy has both criminalised people attending the Climate Camp at Gogarburn based on conjecture, and irresponsibly publicised these allegations to the press. This has amounted to a smear campaign against Climate Camp on the grounds of an unsubstantiated implication of putting &amp;lsquo;many members of the public at risk&amp;rsquo;.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; &quot;The lack of due process and evidence behind these public accusations represents a violation of the responsibility of the police to behave with fairness, integrity and impartiality toward the public.&quot;&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; A spokesperson from the Climate Camp said:&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; &amp;ldquo;It is astounding that the police expect to get away with unfounded accusations against protesters.We do take direct action against the causes of climate change and the severity of the climate crisis sometimes necessitates breaking the law.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; &quot;However, our actions have always been targeted at climate criminals - banks, corporations and governments - and have never aimed to endanger the public.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; A full copy of the letter will be available on Monday at&lt;br&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://climatecamp.org.uk/blog/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://climatecamp.org.uk/blog/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; NOTES FOR EDITORS&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; (1) Climate Camp Update, Lothian and Borders Police 1200hrs, 23/08/10&lt;br&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lbp.police.uk/press_release/articles/2010%5CAugust%5C23%5C2.htm&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://www.lbp.police.uk/press_release/articles/2010%5CAugust%5C23%5C2.htm&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt; Climate Camp - round up of today's activity, Lothian and Borders Police, 23/08/10&lt;br&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lbp.police.uk/press_release/articles/2010%5CAugust%5C23%5C5.htm&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://www.lbp.police.uk/press_release/articles/2010%5CAugust%5C23%5C5.htm&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; (2) The Lothian &amp;amp; Borders Policing Charter:&lt;br&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lbp.police.uk/freedom-of-information/publications/Policing%20Charter.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://www.lbp.police.uk/freedom-of-information/publications/Policing%20Charter.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt; and the Scottish Police Service's Code of Ethical Practice:&lt;br&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.acpos.police.uk/Documents/Policies/PS%20-%20Code%20of%20Ethical%20Practice.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://www.acpos.police.uk/Documents/Policies/PS%20-%20Code%20of%20Ethical%20Practice.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; (3) At the Kingsnorth Climate Camp the Kent Police accused protesters of causing dozens of injuries to police officers, which later turned out to be wasp stings and back aches. (Guardian 16/12/08, 'Minister apologises for police insect injuries' -&lt;br&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.guardian.co.uk/environment/2008/dec/16/kingsnorth-environment-police-inquiry-injuries&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://www.guardian.co.uk/environment/2008/dec/16/kingsnorth-environment-police-inquiry-injuries&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Kent Police also claimed that they had confiscated stockpiles of weapons and dangerous materials from protesters - these items included a board game, crayons, and soap. (Guardian 1/3/09, 'Police &quot;over the top&quot; at climate camp -&lt;br&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.guardian.co.uk/politics/2009/mar/01/kingsnorth-power-station-climate-camp&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://www.guardian.co.uk/politics/2009/mar/01/kingsnorth-power-station-climate-camp&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; (4) At the G20 protests in London (April 2009), which included the Climate Camp in the City, Met Police alleged that they were prevented from helping Ian Tomlinson due to protesters throwing bottles, (Telegraph 2/4/09 'G20 protests: man who died during demonstrations named as Ian Tomlinson' -&lt;br&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.telegraph.co.uk/finance/financetopics/g20-summit/5095080/G20-protests-man-who-died-during-demonstrations-named-as-Ian-Tomlinson.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://www.telegraph.co.uk/finance/financetopics/g20-summit/5095080/G20-protests-man-who-died-during-demonstrations-named-as-Ian-Tomlinson.html&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;br&gt; whereas in reality Ian Tomlinson death was caused by police assault, and protesters were the first to attempt to aid him. (Guardian 22/7/10 'Ian Tomlinson: a story of justice denied' -&lt;br&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.guardian.co.uk/uk/2010/jul/22/ian-tomlinson-story-justice-denied&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://www.guardian.co.uk/uk/2010/jul/22/ian-tomlinson-story-justice-denied&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
      </content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <published>2010-08-24T16:00:00Z</published>
      <updated>2010-08-24T16:00:00Z</updated>
      <title>Superglue Protester's Identity Revealed As Climate Camp Ends</title>
      <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://climatecamp.org.uk/press/2010/08/24/superglue-protester-s-identity-revealed-as-climate-camp-ends" />
      <id>http://climatecamp.org.uk/press/2010/08/24/superglue-protester-s-identity-revealed-as-climate-camp-ends</id>
      <content type="html">
        &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Climate Camp draws to a close and protesters return field to original condition&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Protesters accuse police of scaremongering&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Secret identity of woman super-glued to front desk of RBS revealed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt; After a week of direct actions, the Camp for Climate Action protest outside of RBS HQ at Gogarburn draws to a close and protestors work to return site to its original state.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; &amp;ldquo;Climate Camp is bewildered by police claims of oil being spilled on a main road, and we have no knowledge who was responsible for it if the incident did take place. All the other actions using oil-like substance were molasses, a sugar-based substance.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; &amp;ldquo;Breaking the law to stop climate crimes from happening has become a necessity, but our protests never aim to endanger the public&amp;rdquo;&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; The secret identity of the woman who superglued herself to RBS HQ reception desk last Friday has been revealed as Dongaria Kondh. The protester, who prefers to keep her former name secret, had changed her legal name to that of an indigenous community threatened by RBS-financed mineral extraction company Vedanta. She refuses to change her name back until the Dongria Kondh are given back their land.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; After she was removed from the front desk, she was held for 75 hours, and bailed away from Lothian and Edinburgh on a charge of Breach of the Peace. She has been involved in a successful campaign against a coal mine in the area where she raised her children.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; She entered the building intending to speak with Andrew Cave from the sustainability office, and announced herself as Dongaria Kondh. She had taken with her a report commissioned by the Indian government which concluded that Vedanta has illegally enclosed and occupied land belonging to the Dongaria Kondh, and consistently violated numerous environmental laws in active collusion with state officials. She had previously sent the report to Andrew Cave, and had attempted to arrange a meeting with him but received no reply to her email.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; Ms Kondh said, &amp;ldquo;It seems so unfair that bullyboy corporations can ride roughshod over people who just want to continue their lives living in harmony with their environment. When I heard last week that a tribal leader had been murdered and 2 others tortured by police, I felt that I had to do something to help. I remembered the film in which the rebel slaves all stand up and say &amp;ldquo;I am Spartacus&amp;rdquo; and that gave me the idea to change my name to Dongaria Kondh.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; &amp;ldquo;Supergluing yourself to a table and reading out loud is a pretty harmless thing to do, but I hope my action will help shine the light of day onto what is really going on and where OUR money is really&lt;br&gt; going after the banking collapse. I am feeling a bit worn out after 75 hours in custody, but I hope it&amp;rsquo;s been worth it.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; ENDS&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; For interviews and photographs, contact: &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:press@climatecamp.org.uk&quot;&gt;press@climatecamp.org.uk&lt;/a&gt; / 07040 900 905&lt;br&gt; Photographs can be viewed at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.climatecamp.org.uk/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;www.climatecamp.org.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; NOTES&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; -Vedanta, who run bauxite mining operations in the Niyamairi hills of India, has previously come under fire &amp;nbsp;for its disastrous human rights and environmental record. Protests at Vedanta&amp;rsquo;s AGM received widespread attention. The report describes that the forest-based livelihoods of the local communities and a rich wildlife habitat, including an elephant corridor, is being threatened by Vedanta&amp;rsquo;s operations in the area.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; - Dongria Kondh&amp;rsquo;s trial will be in March. She can be contacted at 07847815926 for interviews.&lt;/p&gt;
      </content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <published>2010-08-23T16:54:00Z</published>
      <updated>2010-08-23T16:54:00Z</updated>
      <title>RBS Operations Closed for the Day as Activists Target Sites around Edinburgh</title>
      <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://climatecamp.org.uk/press/2010/08/23/rbs-operations-closed-for-the-day-as-activists-target-sites-around-edinburgh" />
      <id>http://climatecamp.org.uk/press/2010/08/23/rbs-operations-closed-for-the-day-as-activists-target-sites-around-edinburgh</id>
      <content type="html">
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Action Round-up for the Climate Camp day of mass action targeting RBS&lt;br&gt; and the fossil fuel industry: Monday 23 August&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; Activists at the Camp for Climate Action are celebrating a successful day targeting various climate criminals- holding direct actions, demonstrations and street theatre confronting the role of financial&lt;br&gt; institutions like RBS in bankrolling climate change.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; A group of protestors occupied the head offices of Forth Energy, a company planning to build four new biomass power stations in Scotland. Three protestors chained themselves to the front of the building, two occupied the inside of the office, and two more dropped a banner from the roof of the office. Five arrests were made.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; Simultaneously, seven protestors blockaded the RBS executive carpark at the Gyle Industrial Estate by super-gluing themselves together.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; A group of demonstrators dropped a two metre long piggy bank branded with the RBS logo filled with 60 litres of oil-like substance (molasses) outside the headquarters of Cairn Energy, a company which is coming under fire for its Arctic oil drilling operations. The Greenpeace ship Esperanza is currently engaged in a situation with the Danish Navy off the coast of Greenland with regards to Cairn Energy&amp;rsquo;s drilling operations.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; A group of protestors, including Fringe performers, shut down the Nicolson Street RBS branch. Three individuals super-glued themselves across the front doorway, while another group played music and danced while handing out leaflets. There were three arrests.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; After the previous group of protestors was removed by police, a group of &amp;ldquo;tar-covered&amp;rdquo; protestors shut down the Nicolson St RBS branch a second time, as several activists locked themselves onto the building.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; Activists lay siege to RBS HQ with a six metre tall mock siege tower on wheels with a life-size papier mache rhinoceros head mounted on the front.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A banner was dropped from a building reading &amp;ldquo;oil tar sands = environmental chaos&amp;rdquo;, there were two arrests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another banner was dropped over the A8 which read &amp;ldquo;RBS: using our money to fuck the planet&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Above a tent protest by North Bridge, demonstrators scaled two storeys of scaffolding to drop a banner which read &amp;ldquo;RBS funds and profits from climate chaos&amp;rdquo;&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; Actions in previous days have included:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Hundreds of activists in boilers suits stormed the RBS headquarters, catapulting oil-like substance (molasses) onto the building and attempting to get inside the building. There were two arrests.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; A group of activists caused the closure of RBS bank branches in town by performing a spoof song-and-dance version of Lady Gaga&amp;rsquo;s number one hit &amp;ldquo;Pokerface&amp;rdquo;, rewriting the lyrics to talk about RBS&amp;rsquo; funding of fossil fuels. They invaded an RBS-sponsored stage on the Royal Mile and performed the routing for passers by.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; A group of 40-50 street theatre activists exposed how RBS&amp;rsquo; PR masks the reality of its investments by performing &amp;ldquo;Greenwash Guerrilla&amp;rdquo; street theatre at Gogarburn and the Royal Mile.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; On Saturday, several hundred activists launched an incursion into the RBS HQ complex and held a dance party in the foyer as one activist gained access to the reception area and superglued herself to the front desk.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt; So far, there have been 14 arrests throughout the duration of the camp (from Wednesday evening through Monday afternoon).&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; The Climate Camp have expressed bewilderment as to police claims of oil being spilled on a main road, and have no knowledge who was responsible for it if the incident did take place.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; Harry Reynolds who took part in the actions said:&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; &amp;ldquo;No one came to work today at the RBS Gogarburn headquarters. Since we had already effectively shut that down, we decided to concentrate our energies targeting RBS and its fossil fuel affiliates in the Edinburgh city centre. We&amp;rsquo;ve done a lot to disrupt RBS dirty energy operations today, but we are committed to keeping up the pressure until we manage to cut off the flow of capital from the banks to the fossil fuel industry.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; Natalie Swift, a spokesperson for Climate Camp, commented on the day of action:&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; &amp;ldquo;Today we have seen people tackling RBS&amp;rsquo; responsibility for the billions of pounds it provides to environmentally destructive and dangerous fossil fuel projects. We are being failed by the government and financial institutions, and we are creating a vibrant social movement that takes direct action against the causes of climate change when politicians and bankers fail to do so.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; Photos:&lt;br&gt; Photos of the camp and actions are available at:&lt;br&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.climatecamp.org.uk/actions/edinburgh-2010/photography&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://www.climatecamp.org.uk/actions/edinburgh-2010/photography&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt; They will be updated throughout the day with further photos from actions.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; Videos:&lt;br&gt; The making of the Trojan Pig used at Cairn Energy action&lt;br&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youandifilms.com/2010/08/ribs-the-trojan-pig-makes-a-mess-at-cairn-energy/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://www.youandifilms.com/2010/08/ribs-the-trojan-pig-makes-a-mess-at-cairn-energy/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt; Raising a Ruckus- a short film covering the site take and the first&lt;br&gt; incursion into RBS&lt;br&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ATJwdb4b2Tc&amp;amp;feature=player_embedded&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ATJwdb4b2Tc&amp;amp;feature=player_embedded&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; Twitter:&lt;br&gt; Updates from actions throughout the day of action, including photos&lt;br&gt; and videos, are available on the Climate Camp Twitter stream:&lt;br&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/climate&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;twitter.com/climate&lt;/a&gt; camp&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; Press releases from throughout the day can be found at:&lt;br&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.climatecamp.org.uk/press&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://www.climatecamp.org.uk/press&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
      </content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <published>2010-08-23T14:41:00Z</published>
      <updated>2010-08-23T14:41:00Z</updated>
      <title>Tar Covered Climate Activists Shut Down Bank</title>
      <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://climatecamp.org.uk/press/2010/08/23/tar-covered-climate-activists-shut-down-bank" />
      <id>http://climatecamp.org.uk/press/2010/08/23/tar-covered-climate-activists-shut-down-bank</id>
      <content type="html">
        &lt;p&gt;A group of 'tar' covered activists from the Camp for Climate Action have locked themselves to the RBS branch on Nicholson Street, shutting the bank down. This is the second time that the Nicholson Street bank branch has been shut down by protests today, as several activists who had blockaded the bank entrance by supergluing themselves together in front of it had just been removed by the police, resulting in three arrests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anorther group of activists is demonstrating with banners and leaflets outside the bank branch and on the streets of Edinburgh today targetting RBS branches and sponsored events to expose the extent of Festival sponsor RBS's involvement in climate crimes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The activists are calling for a moratorium on all new investent and loan financing in Tar Sands and other fossil fuels projects. Royal Bank of Scotland is the UK's largest investor in companies operating in the Tar Sands and financed 7.5 billion US dollars worth of loans between 2007 and 2009. One of these companies is Enbrgide, whose controversial proposed Northern Gateway Passage would be laid through British Columbia, across more than fifty First Nation territories and prestine eco-systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Gateway project will cross over 1000 rivers and streams. No oil extraction is safe and secure but given Enbridge has a history of spills from its pipelines this project poses a serious risk to endangered salmon populations which use these rivers to spawn. Any spill will also contaminate the plants and animals that local First Nations depend upon for food and medicine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The action is in solidarity with First Nation peoples who experience the harshest and most immediate effects of RBS's inventments. The activists are concerned that any contamination could mirror the horrific health impacts,&amp;nbsp; including rare cancers, seen in First Nation communities who live near Tar Sands extraction zones. Two members of the First Nation communities have been at Climate Camp this week, speaking of the destruction of their territory and the tragic human cost of the Tar Sands mega project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jasmine Thomas, a member of the frog clan from Saik'uz, which is part of the Carrier Nation, said &quot;Tar Sands is a global phenomenon. It is the largest industrial project in the world. It is also the dirtiest. Tar Sands produces three times as much CO2 per barrel as conventional oil. There's enough underground to push us over the edge into runaway climate change. It should be everyone's concern&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Daniel Balla, one of the activists involved, commented &quot;We feel compelled to take action against RBS as it is now 84% owned by the UK taxpayer. People may be unaware that the institution using vast amounts of public money is investing in the most destructive carbon-emitting industries in the world. Since the bank was bailed out by the British Goverment, 99% of RBSs financing of the energy sector has been pumped into fossil fuels. The future RBS is currently funding will be further polluted,&lt;br&gt;oil-addicted and incur a tragic loss of Indigenous Peoples and degredation of the environment&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
      </content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <published>2010-08-23T10:45:00Z</published>
      <updated>2010-08-23T10:45:00Z</updated>
      <title>RBS branch shut down with superglue and music</title>
      <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://climatecamp.org.uk/press/2010/08/23/rbs-branch-shut-down-with-superglue-and-music" />
      <id>http://climatecamp.org.uk/press/2010/08/23/rbs-branch-shut-down-with-superglue-and-music</id>
      <content type="html">
        &lt;p&gt;People opposed to Royal Bank of Scotland&amp;rsquo;s investments in oil tar sands have super-glued themselves to its Edinburgh Nicholson Street branch, situated at the centre of the City. They were joined by performers angry at RBS&amp;rsquo; sponsorship of the Edinburgh Fringe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One participant, Jenny South, said &amp;ldquo;Climate change kills 400,000 people every year. RBS invests in oil from Canadian tar sands &amp;ndash; the most climate-busting fuel on the planet, and one which is devastating local indigenous communities. We are standing together with those communities to resist this 21st century atrocity, to make a passionate call for climate justice, and to hasten a much-needed fossil fuel-free future.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The action is one part of a mass day of direct action called by The Camp for Climate Action, which has been camped opposite RBS&amp;rsquo; global headquarters in Gogarburn for the last week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ENDS&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more information about Climate Camp and RBS&amp;rsquo; investment in tar sands visit www.climatecamp.org.uk&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
      </content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <published>2010-08-23T10:07:00Z</published>
      <updated>2010-08-23T10:07:00Z</updated>
      <title>Climate Camp art activists cause 'oil' spill outside Cairn Energy</title>
      <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://climatecamp.org.uk/press/2010/08/23/climate-camp-art-activists-cause-oil-spill-outside-cairn-energy" />
      <id>http://climatecamp.org.uk/press/2010/08/23/climate-camp-art-activists-cause-oil-spill-outside-cairn-energy</id>
      <content type="html">
        &lt;p&gt;An 'oil' spill was caused outside the offices of Cairn Energy in central Edinburgh this morning. Activists targeted the Scottish energy company because it used public money from RBS to help it start drilling for oil off the coast of Greenland last month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;The art activis&lt;/span&gt;ts who met at the Climate Camp carried a two metre long piggy bank branded with the RBS logo filled with 60 litres of an oil like substance towards Cairn Energy's offices. Triggered by a golden coin representing the public money used to bail out the bank, the RBS 'piggy bank' unleashed its contents, believed to be molasses, covering the entrances and the street. Activists also sprayed 'oil' on the outside of the building with fire extinguishers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was revealed yesterday that Cairn Energy received &amp;pound;117 million of loans and equity last year from RBS, almost half of which directly enabled the drilling off the Greenland coast to start. This drilling is particularly controversial because the area hasn't been exploited for oil before and has only been made possible as climate change has caused icebergs in this region to melt. T&lt;span&gt;he BP Deepwater oil spill has clearly shown the dangers of offshore drilling and it's argued that Cairn don't have the experience to deal with accidents in the previously pristine and extremely environmentally sensitive Arctic. (A spill in the area would be almost impossible to clean up due to the thick ice.)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alex Wilson, one of the activists who undertook the action said:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;RBS doesn't just sponsor the Edinburgh Fringe, it sponsors the oil companies who destroy the lives of hundreds of millions of people around the world through oil spills, war, drought and floods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Risky drilling in the Arctic by Cairn Energy has only been made possible by financial involvement by RBS. This is an outrageous use of over a hundred million pounds of public money given the economic and climate crises that we are facing.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The activists say that this is the start of a new focus on taking direct action against the oil industry. A mass day of action dubbed 'The Crude Awakening' is already being planned and is set to take place in October in London.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rachel Stone said:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;We have got the oil industry in our sights. We will be targeting the pumps, airports and factories that oil flows through. We will be taking direct action to switch off oil because it is at the heart of the climate crisis that we are all facing.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ENDS&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more information, interviews or print quality photos please call 07040 900 905&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Photos: &lt;a title=&quot;This external link will open in a new window&quot; href=&quot;http://tweetphoto.com/40862372&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://tweetphoto.com/40862372&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a title=&quot;This external link will open in a new window&quot; href=&quot;http://tweetphoto.com/40862372&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;br&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notes to editors&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;According to Bloomberg figures released yesterday Cairn Energy received &amp;pound;117 million in equity and loans.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For more information on the Camp for Climate Action see &lt;a title=&quot;This external link will open in a new window&quot; href=&quot;http://www.climatecamp.org.uk/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;www.climatecamp.org.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For more information about the Crude Awakening &amp;ndash; day of action in October go to &lt;a title=&quot;This external link will open in a new window&quot; href=&quot;http://www.crudeawakening.org.uk/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;www.crudeawakening.org.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
      </content>
    </entry>
  
</feed>

